[Music]
happy sabbath and welcome to living mana
seventh day adventist church we are so
excited to have you here with us this is
our online church and we are just so
thankful to have this platform to be
able to reach as many people
uh in the world through this platform
and we are just so happy that you are
here with us uh today this is our
sabbath school time where we talk about
the bible we talk about current events
as it pertains to the bible and so we
have been talking uh for the last
several weeks we've been actually i
think since april 9th i was thinking
about that today we've been talking with
dr white about
anger
um and we've been going through uh the
sanctuary how the sanctuary helps us
with that uh emotion and just you know
god's way is uh in the sanctuary we have
seen um that through the sanctuary there
are so many answers to so many problems
that we have and so we are going to this
is actually our grand finale on that
topic dr white will be back with us uh
today i think we took a three week break
from this topic because we were covering
the current event um and then dr white
was away last week um and we went and
covered back to the basics many people
said they were blessed by that hopefully
you went back to the youtube channel and
looked at all 10 of back to the basics
um because it really goes into depth um
there and so
let me say that we think
this is going to be the last of the
anger okay the sanctuary see what the
holy spirit dies
just know that i think the first time we
went on we were just thinking of like
you know doing a session or two right um
and it turned into something much bigger
much longer
so uh we are we're going to see how it
goes today
and um the plan is to complete this
today
we'll see how it goes but but i'm glad
that you know from the response we've
been getting people have been blessed
yes
by the series and we're thankful for
that yes we also as usual we want to
know where you are
watching from before we went live um i
saw that people were on from canada and
belize i saw houston texas uh let us
know uh where you're watching from
coffee springs alabama we're in alabama
too i don't know where coffee springs is
but
welcome welcome welcome welcome we are
so happy that you're here what um
california of course my home state
welcome
i we also want you if this is your first
time watching or visiting with us today
um i want you to put a one we want to do
a special welcome to you today um and if
you're a if you're a regular what number
do we want to give for a regular um
a seven if you're a regular that's the
number i was thinking good a seven
um okay we have australia melbourne
australia welcome happy savage
canada sacramento
florida
yes i see oh i see lots of sevens and
there welcome to our regular
uh
viewers and um
i want to say member visitors to our
church
our regulars welcome
okay
no ones yet so i guess everybody is a
regular
with that said
what i'd like for you to do right now is
to is to is to like this link wherever
you're watching if you're watching on
youtube like it and then share it if you
are on facebook
like it and share it
um because that will that lets people
know like hey they're here you can put
on your social media like come join me
this is where i'm worshiping today
whatever you want to say you don't have
to say what i said but
whatever you uh you think but just push
like and share this link um on your
social media uh platform
welcome i see um oh that's nice that's a
nice town to live in happy valley happy
valley oregon
like where do you live happy valley
everybody is happy there that's that's
an interesting but a a very cheerful
name yeah
and welcome god's point of view i saw
one next to next to that name so yes
welcome and any other visitors that are
watching um we just want to welcome you
um
[Music]
and uh yeah we are
we're excited about today's uh today's
program yes we are uh we're going to
bring on dr white shortly we're going to
pray yes um and uh
by the way so i think we should mention
this now okay um
so we are
we're we're
you know all this is new for us so
when we were on the east coast we were
running the uh the church at a
particularly well we are on the west
coast sorry yeah we never we're on these
uh we were uh doing the online church
service at a certain time
we have now moved you know to the east
coast we're in the central uh standard
time zone and
uh we're experimenting with the time
yeah and so
um it is
highly likely that next week
uh or within the next two weeks
uh we may change the time by an hour or
two maybe a little bit later than we are
doing now
uh we're trying to find that sweet spot
uh to you know kind of reach as many
people as we can so
it's not certain we're just testing
these things out
but we just wanted to you know kind of
give you a heads up
uh so that you are you are aware of that
yes yes so
and you will know you will get a
notification and um information about
that before that actually happens but
that is something that we are thinking
about also after um
the the sermon i'm gonna do this too how
many of you have participated in the
afterglow the after sermon um if you
have put a one in the chat um it has
been absolutely amazing um the community
as i say every week is being formed in
altar live after
uh the sermon is over because people are
our p we have our prayer team is there
uh we are are there as well but um the
the prayer team is there we have had um
sister patrice leading out brother
charles leading out and just to hear
your
responses and your
for after the sermon and also if you
have special prayer requests people are
praying all i can say is there's a lot
of love laughter prayers and tears it is
really turning into
a family a community there and the um
altar live for the afterglow uh for
after the sermon so what i want you to
do
if you have not participated i'm seeing
the ones praise god
if you have not participated and don't
have that app downloaded we're going to
put that link now in the chat so you can
do that and if you are wanting to join
um the afterglow the after sermon um
then you can just go to altar live
and i know that my husband pastor myers
will also mention this at the end of his
sermon as well just as a reminder but
but the it's been put in the chat now so
you can download that app so you can
participate and be a part of alter live
and just come and check it out i have to
say that it's yeah you don't you don't
even have to speak you some people are
kind of like oh you're not
no from yeah you don't have to say
anything if you're an introvert or
whatever and you don't feel comfortable
talking you don't have to but you can
you can hear each other's voices you can
see each other
but you don't have to do that but the
option is there
versus just with
uh when we're live streaming like this
we can just put in the chat and so we
can just see each other's names and
maybe the profile picture but that's it
so this makes it a little bit more
intimate you get to get to know each
other
if that's what you're choosing to do but
even if you don't do that just
hearing the prayers and hearing the
testimonies
is truly
truly a blessing
we also want to let you know that we
have a new program starting on tuesday
true health tuesday is starting
this tuesday
um and that's with dr schweltz he's a md
and dr khanisha reynolds who's a
naturopathic doctor they are going to be
um
answering your questions and um just i'm
not sure what their first topic is but i
know it's going to be amazing because
these are two medical minds
that
just all i can say is they're amazing um
a lot of people have been looking
forward to it yeah so yeah it's we've
been talking about this for about uh the
whole time we've yes yeah it was just
since we started that it's coming it's
finally here it's finally here so that
starts this tuesday so mark your your
calendars notifications or whatever and
if you and if you're subscribed which
you should be subscribe to these
channels like the youtube channel if
you're watching on on one of those if
you subscribe you'll get notifications
when we're live so uh just
um all information that you're needing
if you're if you subscribe you will get
that um in a timely manner so i'm
excited for that if you've enjoyed
mental health mondays if you've enjoyed
dr pandit on thursdays you are going to
love
um true health tuesdays oh how could we
forget wednesday night power power
wednesday is starting this week as well
and actually brother terry will be on a
little bit later are at the beginning of
the
divine worship and he'll be able to
share more about that so
power wednesday is also starting i have
to tell you he told us that
they have a prayer team of about
20 people he said so these this is a
prayer team that is serious they pray
during church service they pray when
we're on mondays for mental health
mondays they're going to be praying
uh they pray they're praying right now
they're praying right now they pray
throughout the they're all all
throughout the week over these requests
so
through every program that we have
they're praying and they're praying over
your specific requests so please put in
the chat if you have a prayer request
they are going to be they they're
looking at the chat now so they can get
the prayer request
uh brother terry will be doing the
prayer time but they but the um he can't
do all the prayer requests uh at that
one time and so uh the prayer team
collectively your prayers will be being
prayed over so please put that in the
chat um and just know that your prayers
requests will be being prayed over and
did we forget dr pandit
i mentioned him but okay but dr pandit's
program has been amazing um every
thursday um i think it's six central
seven eastern time um and
just the way that he breaks down he just
makes it
so i don't
i wanna say simple but it he just makes
it so plain that it seems like it's
simple yeah
um on how to prove god's existence
without the bible to a non-believer to
an atheist to a hindu to a whoever that
just doesn't really believe in god and
we need this as christians right if
somebody doesn't believe in the bible
you can't use the bible to prove to them
that god exists because they don't
believe in the bible so we have to prove
god has been so merciful to us that he's
given us so many other ways to prove his
existence and dr pandit
goes through that goes through that on
thursday evening so it's really been a
blessing so our church is really
starting to come together in the sense
that we are not just here on sabbath
that is not our goal our goal is to be
here
all throughout the week and so we're
still going to be growing but just
adding power wednesday and the true
health
tuesdays
is really going to
just add to our weekly uh nightly um
services and please share that because i
know you know someone who needs
uh
some medical information that would be
beneficial to them because we're human
and in the sinful life and world we all
could benefit from some health
um
information that that could help us and
so please share invite your friends to
join you
to watch on tuesday evening and i
already mentioned like mental health
mondays it has been a blessing um
with dr ricardo white and myself and man
your guys's questions like really fuel
the the program like we have a direction
we're going in and you guys stay with
that but then you like broaden it out
and so it's really been
um
it's really been a blessing and so even
like i said with mental i mean with
physical health i know that you know
someone that can be blessed by a mental
health topic as well and so we're
talking about depression we we talked
about it uh last week and this monday
we're actually going to be off we're not
going to be on but the following a
monday we'll be back and we're going to
continue our topic about depression so
join us with that bring your questions
invite your friends your family your
co-workers everybody invite them if you
think they'll be blessed by that and
we're about to bring uh dr white on
before we do someone's asked about
freestyle wednesday so
we are still going to be running
freestyle wednesdays but we're going to
make a little time adjustment to that
because
our
uh power
wednesday prayer meeting
is obviously starting this weekend we
don't want to conflict with that yeah
and uh freestyle wednesday is a power of
the lamb event it's not actually a
living mana event but people are asking
so
um
you won't see that on the living mana
channel you'll see it on the power of
the lamb channel uh and again i'm gonna
be moving that time so i will you will
see it in the next uh link that we put
up for freestyle wednesday which is
happening this wednesday
i have to say that as they say that was
fire yeah i i was watching as well yeah
it was so you know i usually we have
three people on myself and two guests uh
pastor doggett uh was on with me this
this past wednesday and he there's two
pastor doggetts two pastors
um
senior could not be on with us so it was
just myself and uh doggy jr and uh
it was it was just a tremendous
tremendous blessing in fact
it was such a tremendous blessing that
the sermon i'll be preaching today
is partially based off of that freestyle
amen partially good partially that
should be good that that's how good it
was
um
so anyway let's go ahead and bring dr
white on
and uh
welcome welcome back
doctor
you're muted you're muted so unmute
yourself and then there you go
happy 7th um i was i was enjoying those
announcements i know they kept coming i
felt like wow we could do a whole hour
of announcements
no
but that's a blessing that's a blessing
because a church that's open every you
know day was your was your vision and
it's happening yes it's happening
thank you so much for allowing me to be
away last week
um there is a gentleman from uh
you know basically community
um who was graduating
and um he was graduating from ucla and
it was i don't know if it was four to
six hundred graduates and it was such a
handful of of black men
and so it was such a privilege to
support him and knowing his journey so
congratulations justin
um but thank you so much for allowing me
to make that you know investment uh in
in him uh someone that i've mentored
um so i didn't miss you guys and thank
you for saving the finale and we'll see
if it's the finale but yeah thank you
for saving the finale until now
amen amen and doctor it could be a
little bit on on my side but um
you sound a little low
and i think it's on i'm not gonna say
it's on your side i'm gonna say it's on
our side so for our sakes
uh a tantanam just one of you can just
speak a little louder
three
tests one two three it's on our side
yeah it's on our side it's it's
okay because everybody but yeah everyone
else can hear you so we'll just
we'll fight to hear everything everyone
can hear you good night it's just us
got it very closely yeah
yeah
so
okay yes so um let's jump into prayer
yeah let's pray doc could you lead us
out in prayer absolutely
our father and our god dear lord
um we thank you for this space and time
that you've created uh for for us to be
a conduit of your light
and we pray that
uh
we would be relevant impactful
and and equip your saints with tools
they can use
in the fiery furnace that they are in uh
we pray that you know in the midst of
things they'd be able to draw on this
and to reflect your character in the
process
and we pray this in your holy name
please deal with the distractions and
and help everyone to stay focused so
that they can walk away from this with
something they can take into their life
into their week
um be with pastor tantan uh sister
um myers
because you see what they have to endure
to make this possible bless them keep
them in your holy name we pray amen amen
amen amen amen
so i don't know if we want to do a
little recap or
yeah
i think it's been a break i think we
should probably do a recap
yeah yeah i can go ahead and recap um
so and this will just be a very quick
recap but basically what we have been
talking about is
uh the sanctuary in connection with
the um
uh
the issue of anger
and
we
we we started this whole study because
of the you know very well known slap
that was heard across the world that we
said hey let's deal with the issue of
anger and talk about the solutions
as they are found in the word of god and
particularly the sanctuary and so for
the last several weeks um
we have been looking at each article of
furniture
in the sanctuary
and demonstrating how the altar of their
six articles of furniture each one of
these articles represents a different
principle
in the plan of salvation represents a
different principle in the gospel um and
we've been sharing how each one of these
articles
connect
or offer a solution for dealing with
anger so we've gone through the altar of
sacrifice
uh we've gone through the labor and
we're not gonna you know go back and
watch those series if you're interested
in and you know knowing what did they
represent because if we do a recap like
that that'll be the whole program yes um
but we went through five different
articles the altar of sacrifice
followed by the labor the table of
showbread the altar of incense
and i believe the last one we did was a
seven branch candlestick
and so now we are on the final article
of furniture which is the ark of the
covenant
found in the most holy place there's the
ark there's the mercy seat
um
in the same location and so today we're
going to be talking about anger and how
the articles
found in the most holy place can help to
resolve
the issue of anger before it spills out
and hurts either ourselves or other
people yeah our goal is to just you know
show how the answer is in the sanctuary
uh which is really jesus but he's
showing us through the sanctuary
so that anger doesn't hijack you uh the
way that
so many times it happens in so many of
us uh
every day or throughout the week and so
this was
and is our goal and so we're going to
still be looking at that today sure
yeah
but what i would what i would add to
that is
when you when you recall the purpose of
the sanctuary
god is
reconciling man with god
because the schism because sin had
caused the schism and so now you see as
you go through each article of furniture
notice that it now is ending in the most
holy place
it's bringing you
what what so now what do you encounter
in the most holy place
you encounter the shekinah glory of god
but you've been traveling this path to
get to this point
um
so you see the shekinah glory of god and
that's glorious that's absolutely
amazing you're face to face with god
he's flanked by two covering cherubs two
covering sheriffs you've talked so much
about those um you know cherubs that are
flanking
um
god
because and one of those tariffs of
course signifies none other than lucifer
so here you are being brought into the
presence of god and if you if you if
you've heard you know
sermons talked about you've heard
something doctor i'm gonna incorrupt i'm
gonna interrupt you right there
uh you just said that one of those
angels
was lucifer and um you know there may be
people on who have never heard that
before so i just want to give the
reference
right uh two references you want to go
to isaiah 14 which identifies
lucifer and ezekiel 28 that identifies
him as the covering
yes there were two of them so we know
that he was one
in which uh one of the angels which
stood closest to the presence of god so
that's just for reference sake for those
who may be watching this for the first
time never wait what
that those are the verses that you want
to go go to ezekiel 28 uh particularly
verse 12 on
and isaiah 14
uh verses 12 to 14. and someone wants to
know what the shekinah glory is so i
don't know if you want to explain that
anyway another one of you are no i'm
pastor that's all you that was
all right
so so
the shekinah glory um and i see some
people already answering it in the chat
the shekinah glory simply
represented the presence of god that was
the presence
that dwelt on the mercy seat and you
know the priests could not go into the
sanctuary into the most holy place
without
you know
thorough preparation
that's because they were entering into
the very
presence
of god
right so that's what your kind of glory
was think of it like this this cloud of
smoke and light
that that
was present in
the most holy place
right and so so now i'm going to go back
to the covering cherub and remember this
is in the context of this
of discussing anger
and sometimes you've heard it been said
that when god does not allow the sinner
into heaven it's actually merciful
because a sinner would be miserable in
heaven right and so you're like that
can't be possible i was literally
thinking that can't be possible and then
i thought about the covering cherub
lucifer lucifer was miserable in heaven
he was miserable in heaven and the power
of the reference by uh by pastor myers
just now is when you read those
references it says thou has said in
thine heart so it explains what it is
that he's thinking
you are envying the most high i will be
like the most high he's he's he wants to
he wants to take the spot of god okay
and so he's in heaven miserable and so
what you see is you see this path
that god has the sinner travel
so that you are then prepared to be
reconciled to him so it's it's it's it's
very um
but when you come into that holy place
you now see the shekinah glory of god
symbolizing god and god is seated on
something god is seated on something
that thing is called
the mercy seat
it's called the mercy seat and that
mercy seat
sits
above
the covenant of god
the law
okay
and that law signifying justice
so what we see is the governmental in
the governmental basis of god
mercy
sits above
justice
amen
mercy sits above justice where god lives
where he dwells where he occupies okay
his judgment in in his government
mercy sits above justice how glorious
how how glorious for you and i
because we are so in desperate need of
mercy yeah
so
my question and you know both of you can
you know chime in on this if you want to
but
in a
in the biblical sense
how
how does mercy
work
like how can i make sure
that i remain
under the mercy of god
and how would that tie in
with anger
which is usually exercised towards other
people
hmm
well
well the the interesting thing is i i
think that's the beauty of of the
audience now seeing all of them come
together and end with mercy
because
we saw that we we started at the cross
and we figured out that we are not on
the cross
so that that already arrests your mind
dude you're not on the cross
and a lot of it is you're actually
bringing so much anger to the situation
that has nothing to do with the
situation that you're bringing to it and
so now you saw that the century
recommended that your next step is to go
to the labor and die to self okay you
need to you really those those motives
that are questionable they need to die
and so now you are ready to leave the
courtyard and enter into that holy place
where now you found his word
and a profound question you have to ask
yourself is well what was god's word
well those words we say symbolize the
bible so go back because we went into
detail even with references
but here's the profound question
what is god's word for your life
what is god's word for your life what is
god what is god saying to you
specifically
because
if if you're not listening for his word
then you won't know his word for your
life and if you don't know his word for
your life you won't know his will for
your life
and if you don't know his will
you can't live it
and here is what's profound
faith comes by what
faith comes by hearing and and here's
the here's the thought that hit me this
week as i was listening to
to to some of your programs pastor
faith
the ultimate test of faith
is actually
circumstances overwhelming the senses
but you still remembering what you heard
and adhering to it so your senses are
overwhelmed
but you can recall hey you know what
i i recall hearing god say this through
his word
and god having a living breathing
relationship with you
the test is
will you stick to that will you remember
that when your senses are overwhelmed
the significance of that statement is
the society today is conditioning us to
be hypersensitive to our senses
society today is conditioning us to be
oversensitive to our senses and letting
that rule our behavior
i want to give you an illustration so i
was listening to a navy seal
and he was talking about the six months
of training that he describes as you
know hell
and one
exercise in particular where they're in
a pool
and
they they they have the scuba gear on
them
and in the pool there's a random point
where
the
the um the directors will come down
attack them disorient them and then they
have to figure things out from there and
what he mentioned was you cannot panic
and you must remember
the sequence you must remember the
sequence you cannot let the senses
flood you disorient you overwhelm you
because then you failed the test
i'm saying what if the enemy knows
that that that if we can hear
then we're set up to remember and so he
makes his goal that you never hear it
so that you're not even prepared to fail
the test you already failed by default
because you can't remember something you
didn't take the time to memorize you
can't remember something you never took
the time to hear are you hearing god's
word
and then of course we talked about
praying
that living breathing dialogue with god
and and that experience
then giving you the chance to get to the
the candlesticks where you witness
what you witnessed and that experience
ushering you back into the presence of
god
so i want you to see
that
the sanctuary answers the question that
pastor myers asked you know in terms of
look
what is it
you got to repeat the question pastor
so i was asking how
the process of mercy
right how does it how does it work and
how does it relate to the question we're
talking about which is
when i get angry at other people how
does
how does my reaction yeah or when you
feel that emotion of anger yeah to other
people what does that have to do
with me
and god's mercy
and and i have to bring it all down to
the word
pause
when you get triggered when you feel
angered you have to
pause
because
yes you have to think about mercy
yes
so you have to pause so that it's like
okay before i just before i just do what
my senses want me to do right let me
pause
and i think that's what you were
saying when you're saying society is
trying to to train us not to pause
not to take that note
respond to that emotion let it take you
over do it yeah not to pause
um not to take that time
so
i was just gonna say that that pause
practically what does that look like
that this could be like
a millisecond i mean i don't know it
could be so quick it's not this long it
doesn't have to be this long long pause
but you feel that i like to and i like
to say a tsunami of emotion or anger
um emotion and when you feel that it is
at that time where you need to take the
pause you need to take
because your next step because your next
step after the pause is to see if you
can't move towards mercy yes
mercy look man mercy's been extended to
me when i've needed it
you know
so could it be this person is deserving
of mercy right yeah and and listen
i i don't think it's
could it be that this person is
deserving of mercy
because i know for a fact that i was not
deserving of mercy right
right when god gave me mercy i he didn't
give it to me because i deserved it
so
it's as if god is saying to us
if you want my mercy
i need you to be merciful to others
right
and
that is the exact opposite response that
anger calls for right
anger calls for
vengeance anger calls for you know
justice albeit so many times it's human
justice it's it's corrupt justice
but mercy
is not given to those that
that get it because they deserve it
mercy is given out of a heart of love
that's all it is that that's all it can
be
i like what iris said says pause is in
god's mentality like
yeah think about it like this when
when you
extend mercy
[Music]
you are entering into the presence of
god yes
yes yes think of it now it's like god's
saying okay because it's his principle
it's what it's how god operates yeah he
he says look mercy yeah all of these
things you do like the altar of
sacrifice and the labor you're building
you're getting there you're still
working through the anger
but
until the moment that you extend
mercy
mercy is the thing that leads you into
the presence of god and i think the
amazing cool thing about that is that
when you feel that tsunami of emotion of
of anger and then you pause and then you
hear
god's word from the table of showbread
or whatever um and you decide to
exercise and show mercy not only is it a
blessing to the person
or the situation there's also a blessing
to you
so god is trying to bless you like you
responded in
god's way and so blessings um are you
know you're not gonna have that
feeling of regret at it because you did
you you showed mercy and you did not
give in to this that emotion of tsunami
of anger emotion absolutely and so
god just got god is just good like that
like he will save you from hurting
yourself and hurting someone else at the
same time
so so one pause
so so what's interesting is the the the
process of the sanctuary if you go
through that process of the sanctuary it
sets you up
to be able to recognize and position
yourself to deliver mercy
rather than if you had just gone by your
senses
[Music]
okay so that that's the whole point of
the process by the time you see christ
on the cross by the time you die to self
by the time you bring together relevant
scripture by the time you pray by the
time you pray lord
how would you like to use me in this
situation
i'm available remember remember god's
ultimate
um god's ultimate denunciation of the
wicked i never knew you right
you were never available for use
i never knew you you never came to me
and said just just just use me and use
me as a witness
okay
um so but that's the mercy part that's
the mercy part i know a lot of people
are listening and they're like mercy
mercy mercy mercy well what about
justice
you know what's interesting
you need god for the justice part as
well
first of all our indignation is rarely
if ever righteous
so what's got us indignant is often the
wrong thing
but
even when it's time to give out justice
what's interesting is
we often are ready to extend
mercy
to people who have power over us
but but it's rare for us to actually be
able to take justice to something we're
afraid of
to a power structure that we're afraid
of
no will and mercy sometimes the mercy of
negligence
okay
because it's it's something that if you
dealt with it it would cost you
and and that's the difference with
divine justice
god will meter out mercy
and he he has the courage and the
fairness to deal out justice
both mercy and justice we need god in
order to mediate
because they're both critical
don't have an accurate picture of love
if you don't see the blending of mercy
and justice
where's the intestines
i think
yeah i was just gonna gonna gonna say
here i think when moses
was in the presence of god and god told
him to take off his shoes you're on holy
ground
it was like a moment of
forget everything else that's going on
around you mercy you are in
the presence of god
and we know that sin
cannot dwell
in the presence of god
so
why is god trying to move us into his
presence
wow
right he's trying you know the song turn
your eyes upon jesus look full
in his glorious face and the things of
this earth will grow
strangely
right
it's it's
it's this idea that
if i can get into the presence of god
we talk about worship right we see
people worshiping and people like oh i'm
in the presence of god and you know
being in the presence of god
shuts everything else out
right it it it puts things into their
correct
perspective
and
now that situation that is leading you
to be angry
which
looked huge in your own mind god helps
you in his presence
to see how much bigger he is than that
situation
well well said and the reverse is true
like i think when we engage in behaviors
that are unlike god we often don't want
to then enter into his presence
right
it's like you've you ever watched the
wrong movie and now you don't feel like
praying mm-hmm what i'm saying yeah
and it's like that's when you need god
the most yes
um but i i find that very interesting um
that that analogy that you you raised
pastor because after moses had been in
god's presence
his face was shining so much that he was
blinding to the people around him i
think they can shroud his face if i'm
not mistaken
but but that's what happens when you're
in the presence of god
the world gets dim to you and it's
interesting that you may be blinding to
those around you after being in the
presence of god
there was a comment um and it's kind of
up
up the chat now um i think it was by
kirk and i just thought it was you know
it was saying he said a work in progress
he said that he would you know because
i'm going to put up another comment as
well address that and i want you guys to
okay
um he just said work in progress um
because of the family or origin that uh
family of origin that he was born into
it will be very difficult to apply
these principles to respond in this
godly way and i just you know i just
wanted to encourage him and everyone
else that we're all work in progress
right this tsunami of emotion of anger
is not i don't want us to make this seem
like this is the easiest thing in the
world i mean god
extends grace and mercy to us and
provides us with the power to be able to
do these things uh but when you're in a
situation um and
when you like how uh brother kirk said
like and you were
you've been raised or you have
throughout your life just
easily just given in to the tsunami of
the emotion of anger um
it's you know it's not an easy thing to
just you know change that you're
building new pathways in your brain to
be able to um behave and respond
differently but this information i mean
the bible god he's like revealing to us
like these are the steps that you can
take to be able to change that these are
the steps that can help you build a new
pathway
in your mind um so that this you know
the past behavior does not have to
be
it does not have to be the new or the
current has to stay the same you can
actually create a new behavior and
response um to that so just wanted to
say that you know we're all a work in
progress and it's not uh the the easiest
thing but the first step is to be aware
and to know that okay i don't have to
give in to this and not be of emotion
the way i have throughout my life yeah
and and there's that see the question on
the screen i don't know if you guys can
see it i see it i see it i see i am
going to have i'll hop in on that but i
just wanted to dovetail off of what you
said says it's almost like the sanctuary
is even more effectively used in
hindsight yeah okay in hindsight for
foresight
meaning meaning
the the it is really helpful to explore
past behaviors through the lens of those
sanctuary furnitures
and that will prepare you
to deal with what's coming in the future
so don't think that past failures
um are not good
substrate good
opportunities
for you to get the mind right so that
you don't make the mistake again now the
prior question was okay man what about
what about getting angry
about like someone who's let's say
emotionally abusing a child or worse or
worse
um so scripture is clear the issue is
not getting angry these are god-given
emotions you know we are designed by god
so the emotions we experience they're
god-given so the question is not is it
wrong to get angry the question is
what do you do with the anger
right
what do you do with that anger and so
and what are you getting angry at
and what are you getting angry at is
your indignation righteous is it really
righteous and so so part of the appeal
is okay
you we're angry about the child being
abused
now
so the the person abusing the child you
shoot him you know um that's a mistake
you know what i'm saying it's like um
like so it's what would god have me do
in this situation
like that that that's the thing does the
anger then trigger you to go back and
say god what would you have me do
because god has a phenomenal solution or
he's he's gotten it he's got a
significant thing for you to do when he
reveals it to you will you do it will
you trust him
will you will you exert the patience to
connect with him and then the other
piece that we tend to have as humans is
we often allow the sins that we don't
have to distract us
so so look um let me you know that
really angers me over there while you're
still doing your stuff over here
and so
what you want to condition yourself to
is
you know
god
looks at what i'm doing
probably the same as how i look at that
over there
you know like he like
just just let me appreciate that so that
that can motivate you to recognize that
we need to change and we need to grow
and we need to let that sanctuary make
the changes that it's inclined to um
change
that's how i would answer that
i would also say like and totally
agreements with dr white but also if you
if you're seeing if you know of a child
being abused or you know physically or
sexually then
um of course you know you will feel that
emotion of anger and righteous anger
which uh you should because that is
wrong and then
god yeah god will lead you to do
something as far as you know talking to
the appropriate authorities or whatever
the case may be so that you know that
can that can they can help that help
that child so that will end
but
yeah there's definitely righteous
indignation righteous anger somebody put
in the chat
turning the tables over i mean that's
what jesus did
in the temple because of how they were
treating
his father's house
but but the thing about him turning the
tables over
is god is not
jesus was not doing anything out of step
with god right no
that's the key thing
and
like and for those of us operating in
you know society especially in you know
roles that are high stakes
it is
rare it is rare that a full vent of rage
is productive
rare if ever
like it it's rare if ever
situations that are high stakes usually
require a delicacy
strategy
you know doing things that are
absolutely counter intuitive
um and and so it is so rare that a full
vent of emotions don't actually make
things worse
okay
the command is be angry and sin and not
be angry and don't make the situation
worse
okay and that's why we need the the
divine influence
um to help us so that we don't make
situations worse but we actually can
improve the situation if we at least
pause we at least pause and give god a
chance to guide us into what he would
have us do
that's good there was a question and
it's kind of again it's up in the chat i
don't and i'm not quite sure
if what if they were asking like
is there it was something when you're
getting angry with a child uh i don't
know it's kind of up a little bit
substance something about substance uh
yeah and i'm not sure okay could there
be substances involved in getting angry
with a child i'm not sure well i'm glad
they brought up the issue of substances
because obviously when we're talking
about substances we can often be talking
about alcohol we can talk about drugs
okay
and
one of the things that god really wants
us to do is is to be sober
because
um i you know i mentioned before
that you know with sobriety with the
with the sober mind
you you're more inclined to make the
correct decisions we know when
intoxicated you miss cues you know like
obviously you you know that it's you're
discouraged from driving you know when
you're intoxicated you know so and so
forth because because why you're more
prone to making an accident
but you you know and i know that like if
you've ever been in the audience of a
married couple for example you'll see
them both
cue you that they're leaving and it's
simultaneous and at some point they made
a communication to each other it's time
to go you know what i'm saying not a
good time you don't even see it
sometimes it's just a look sometimes
it's just the touch but what i'm saying
is there's high order communication
that's taking place and so when
intoxicated you can miss cues that are
very very important
and so that that kind of that kind of
sensibility being lost as you're
interacting with a child you can see
how
how vulnerable a person can be to making
really great mistakes interacting with
so tender and experienced
um so
so i i just wanted to kind of add that
um interacting with our children
requires your a game
you you've got to require
require your a game i was having a
conversation with my daughter um just
yesterday and i'm literally like praying
like father how would you like to use me
in this situation literally i'm saying
this because because our goal is to help
our children but sometimes our passions
can lead us to if anything
hurt the relationship and here you're
trying to help them
yes
that that's a really you you i cannot
imagine the disadvantage i would place
myself if i chose to disinhibit myself
a lot of times these situations they
happen without any warning
um so you can see the importance of of
of avoiding these intoxicating
substances where we are not at our best
to deal with these high-stakes
situations especially as we're different
with our children
and i want to say as you know because
when our children do something that
upset us then that pause for a second
and the person asking the question was
not asking about substance as in drugs
but they were saying what you're just
addressing what if there's your child
does something
right that they weren't supposed to do
right that makes you angry so go ahead
so i was gonna say so you feel
going um in line with what dr white was
saying too but just you know you feel
that emotion of that that anger um
because your child just either disobeyed
you did something completely crazy and
you're wondering are they in their right
mind i mean we've all been there right
or you're like what is going on um and
so you feel that emotion and and the
principle is is the same and you know um
you know our there's um our favorite um
christian author she she puts um
that even when you're disciplining
your children
so
again the principles are the same so
when we're disciplining our children it
should still be
uh
showing grace and mercy um and it
doesn't mean they don't have a
punishment or in trouble but your
emotions um should we should always
discipline and love so you're correcting
you're giving a punishment they're the
consequences are still the consequences
but just like we don't want police
officers right to
be
abusive and be brutal and hurt people
when they're arresting them so we're not
to be brutal or abusive either when
we're disciplining our children so you
can still correct them they are still
getting a punishment they're getting in
trouble
but you're showing um that emotion of
love the way that god
deals with us so it's the same principle
so it's it's not like we can yell and
scream at our kids and going on with
what dr white said just in dealing with
our children you don't want to ruin the
relationship right you want them to be
like wow
mom or dad was so calm when they found
out that i did x y and z where uh they
were probably afraid of what mom and dad
were gonna was gonna how they were gonna
respond but when you respond like
god responds with us like yes you're
still gonna have to deal with these
consequences but i love you um and i'm
disappointed but you're showing them a
spirit of love
the the text is train up a child in the
way that he should go it didn't say beat
up a child it didn't say emotionally
abuse a child it said train it's that
train much the way
we train subordinates at work
so how do you train your patient
you establish relationship
you you train
you you you have patience you understand
that they probably aren't going to get
it the first time
um and and and so i find that scripture
so powerful train up your child in the
way that he should go and and that's
profound because it's it's really
according to their bent meaning
you train you deliver the training in
accordance with their inclination
meaning what would work with one child
will not work with another child
say it again we have four
yeah it's like so we had to do four
different things yeah it's like it
really is a challenge of your mastery
because what works with one will not
work with another it's it's learning
each child's language
train and when you see discipline
exerted 9 out of 10 times it's not with
the spirit of training it's with the
spirit of vengeance
how dare you abuse me
you know how do you know how embarrassed
i was
you know it's like it's vengeance it's
not training it's not like we gotta sit
down we gotta talk let's go through this
and so
yeah we're talking about being ushered
into the presence of god we're talking
about a process that is to lead you into
you seeing the shekinah glory of god
and that's the power of that process and
and as it relates to anger
so i think i think like
all together
and i don't know doctor there's anything
else i mean there's a lot more that can
be shared but i think
we have
gone through every article of furniture
and shown the relationship the
connection with and what we're gonna do
is we're gonna
we're gonna put this on a playlist
and on our youtube uh our channel so for
those of you who are to go watch the
living mana youtube you'll be able to
watch all the
um
the entire series in order we're going
to get that done um
but i think this is
i mean
what better answer is possible to
overcoming anger than the steps revealed
in a sanctuary
i don't know of benny
wilson
i don't know of any so i think god has
uh laid this out first in a very
beautiful and significant way
um it is gospel centered
and um
it's
again it's it's god training
that's what he's using the sanctuary to
train us right
right this is how you overcome this so
this is his training ground which kind
of goes
you know along with the series that
we're doing right now god's powerhouse
meaning the sanctuary how do we get
power to overcome these things
um
all very
all comes together go ahead doc
but i i think your sermon on prayer
and and your call to action at the end
was so profound
we don't want the things of god
if we're honest
and if we're visceral like we don't we
don't flesh does not want the things of
god the the first prayer has to be lord
please make me want you
yeah we and i'm talking about in the
midnight hour i'm talking when nobody's
looking i'm talking about when i'm alone
with myself the heart of myself please
make me want you
please make me want these things you
have to do this work i can't do it
that has to be the first prayer and
everything then comes from there and and
the other main point about the sanctuary
is it's um it's a wonderful tool for
rehabilitation
it's a great tool
for looking at things in hindsight
you're going to make mistakes it's going
to happen okay
um even when you think you did it right
look at revisit it through the lens of
the sanctuary and and see what the
training opportunities are for you to
get better for you to get better so that
you're ready for the next high-stakes
situation it comes without warning it
comes without label
you're just in it before you but you're
like what just happened we were having a
peaceful
boom came out of nowhere
but the work the prior work you'll find
that because you've now conditioned the
right reflexes you paused
you paused you didn't just open your
mouth it took 22 years of marriage for
me to realize i can't say the first the
second the third or the fourth thing
that drops into them
you can't
don't do that
not that no not that no not that well
no
uh thank you lord that's the one yeah
yes
being aware is everything knowing like
it took you did you say twenty how many
years did you what two years ago july
yeah
no i was going to say i didn't tell you
but dr white knows because i mentioned
it in mental health mondays that
you know we it took us like 10 years or
so to realize that we
are most of our arguments happen like in
the car in the middle of the night
driving to an airport or going doing
something late at night so we realized
like okay we have to either book earlier
flights we argue
we have to either not i'm saying book
later flights not early flights or if we
do have to go early in the morning we'll
just be silent in the car because
neither of us do well with lack of sleep
and so we became aware of that and so
sometimes i mean not sometimes all the
time you have to realize what your
triggers are too and lack of sleep for
us
is our trigger so yeah my wife and i we
used to listen to this like this song
right um
and without fail
30 seconds after the song we'd be
fighting it was so funny
we had to ban the song
yes
so yeah i i really hope that this series
on anger um has been helpful i hope that
you guys have seen
that the temptation
is to focus
um outward
and say oh look at that over there
that's crazy
rather than instead saying you know what
what what can i learn from that
situation
okay
um and then you also doing the homework
oh my goodness i am so ashamed of how i
responded i am so ashamed
uh let me look at it through the lens of
the sanctuary how can i do things
differently um that's our call to action
is that explore
a past meltdown of yours
explore a past meltdown of yours and and
look at how things could have gotten
been dealt with in a in a better way had
you paused
um
you're ready you're more ready for the
next one
yes amen yes in the chat people have
definitely said that this has been a
blessing um and that they will those who
have missed some of the
um
segments or episodes they will go back
through the playlist and watch and so
we're just so thankful dr white is a
part of the living round of church he's
a board member he we do
mental health mondays every monday um
and so he will be back this was this
series he will be back again
um on another series um
and so and so i know so many people have
been blessed uh by what you have shared
um and so it has just truly been a
blessing to go through this i never
thought
uh we would be going through it this
many weeks but um god god is good that's
good and so hopefully you know you if
you've enjoyed this please share again
with your
uh your family your friends um and just
say hey this is some practical
uh tools and biblical tools um that i've
learned uh through this series and just
say hey this is this is where it's at
and give them the link to the the
playlist on the youtube um so definitely
share this and go over it again this is
something like i said earlier this it's
we're all a work in progress and um and
so this
is something that
you know you're taking baby steps
towards um and god will
he will give power and anoint those
steps and so that the change can
move as quickly as
as he sees you know fit for you to be
able to change that this is what your
heart is really wanting and desiring
for yourself and so again just want to
say thank you to dr white thank you to
all of you who have participated
throughout this
series and have shared comments i liked
what somebody said she said when her
teenager does something she puts herself
on a as a parent she puts herself on a
timeout first
and then she addresses uh the teenager
that is like that's that's real wisdom
and that's the pause that time out is
really the pause and so uh we just
praise god for for that comment and that
and that insight
we want to we want you to continue to
worship with us as uh we will be moving
into
uh the divine uh worship uh time we have
some special
uh things a special testimony that will
be uh coming up you don't want to miss
that um and uh we just
pray that you would um share again this
link at this time you could invite
someone say hey come join me for church
and when they realize they don't even
have to leave their home get in their
car or do anything like that they just
have to click a button
and
they will they will be there you know
what i wonder if we can bring dr white
back because yeah we didn't end in
prayer
we were just going to end in prayer
together but definitely share with your
with your your friends you don't want to
miss uh the divine worship service and
right after we pray we're going to go
into evangelist taj apocalypse
reflection of hope
which is always filled with tons of hope
yeah
any any final words you want to share
and then would you lead us out in prayer
uh you're muted you're
muted sorry about that yeah i i just
wanted to say this was such a pleasure
such an honor it was it was such a
pleasure to be able to refer hey sis
what do you think of this or pastor
what's the reference here
and it was just such a retreat so i look
forward to you know coming back being a
you know source please use me
and
we will use you you'll be back
this was really fun shall we bow our
heads for prayer
our father and our god um we thank you
for your word we thank you for solving
things before they were a problem
so we thank you for the sanctuary
that that shows us your way and and the
logical process that we can use to deal
with the things we're struggling with
so um please remember to use it even in
hindsight
re-explore areas that we can make better
and we pray that you would grant us a
glorious day where we would be able to
stand on that sea of glass and testify
of how we got over
um through the power of the blood of the
lamb we pray this in your holy name amen
amen amen
amen god bless guys god bless